<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>/home/dprince</title><link href="https://dprince.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://dprince.github.io/feeds/all-en.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://dprince.github.io/</id><updated>2017-01-25T09:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Docker Puppet</title><link href="https://dprince.github.io/docker-puppet.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-25T09:00:00-05:00</published><author><name>Dan Prince</name></author><id>tag:dprince.github.io,2017-01-25:docker-puppet.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today TripleO leverages Puppet to help configure and manage the
deployment of OpenStack services. As we move towards using Docker
one of the big questions people have is how will we generate config files
for those containers. We'd like to continue to make use of our mature
configuration interfaces (Heat parameters, Hieradata overrides, Puppet modules)
to allow our operators to seamlessly take the step towards a fully
containerized deployment. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out with the with the recently added composable service we've got
everything we need. This is how we do it...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Install puppet into our base container image&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out the first thing you need of you want to generate config files
with Puppet is well... puppet. TripleO uses containers from the Kolla
project and by default they do not install Puppet. In the past TripleO
uses an 'agent container' to manage the puppet installation requirements.
This worked okay for the compute role (a very minimal set of services)
but doesn't work as nicely for the broader set of OpenStack services because
packages need to be pre-installed into the 'agent' container in order for
config file generation to work correctly (puppet overlays the default config
files in many cases). Installing packages for all of OpenStack and its
requirements into the agent container isn't ideal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter TripleO composable services (thanks Newton!). TripleO now supports
composability and Kolla typically has individual containers
for each service so it turns out the best way to generate config files
for a specific service is to use the container for the service itself. We
do this in two separate runs of a container: one to create config files, and
the second one to launch the service (bind mounting/copying in the configs).
It works really well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we still have the issue of how do we get puppet into all of our Kolla
containers. We were happy to discover that Kolla supports a template-overrides
mechanism (A jinja template) that allows you to customize how containers
are built. This is how you can use that mechanism to add puppet into
the Centos base image used for all the OpenStack docker containers generated
by Kolla build scripts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ cat template-overrides.j2
&lt;span class="o"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;% extends parent_template %&lt;span class="o"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;% &lt;span class="nb"&gt;set&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;base_centos_binary_packages_append&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;puppet&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; %&lt;span class="o"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

kolla-build --base centos --template-override template-overrides.j2
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h1&gt;Control the Puppet catalog&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A puppet manifest in TripleO can do a lot of things like installing packages,
configuring files, starting a service, etc. For containers we only want to
generate the config files. Furthermore we'd like to do this without having to
change our puppet modules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One mechanism we use is the --tags option for 'puppet apply'. This option
allows you to specify which resources within a given puppet manifest (or catalog) should be executed. It works really nicely to allow you to select what
you want out of a puppet catalog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example of this is listed below where we have a manifest to create
a '/tmp/foo' file. When we run the manifest with the 'package' tag
(telling it to only install packages) it does nothing at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ cat test.pp 
file &lt;span class="o"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;/tmp/foo&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;:
  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;content&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;bar&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,
&lt;span class="o"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
$ puppet apply --tags package test.pp
Notice: Compiled catalog &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; undercloud.localhost in environment production in 0.10 seconds
Notice: Applied catalog in 0.02 seconds
$ cat /tmp/foo
cat: /tmp/foo: No such file or directory
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h1&gt;When --tags doesn't work&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out out --tags option of 'puppet apply' doesn't always give us the
behavior we are after which is to generate only config files. Some puppet
modules have custom resources with providers that can execute commands anyway.
This might be a mysql query or an openstackclient command to create a keystone
endpoint. Remember here that we are trying to re-use puppet modules from
our baremetal configuration and these resources are expected to be in
our manifests... we just don't want them to run at the time we are generating
config files. So we need an alternative mechanism to suppress (noop out)
these offending resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do this we've started using a custom built noop_resource function that
exists in puppet-tripleo. This function dynamically configures a default
provider for the named resource. For mysql this ends up looking like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="x"&gt;[&amp;#39;Mysql_datadir&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;Mysql_user&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;Mysql_database&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;Mysql_grant&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;Mysql_plugin&amp;#39;].each |String &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;val&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="x"&gt;| &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="x"&gt; noop_resource(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;val&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="x"&gt;) }&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Running a puppet manifest with this at the top will noop out any of the named
resource types and they won't execute. Thus allowing puppet apply to complete
and finish generating the config files within the specified manifest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is most of our services don't require the noop_resource in
order to generate config files cleanly. But for those that do the interface
allows us to effectively disable the resources we don't want to execute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Putting it all together: docker-puppet.py&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bringing everything together in tripleo-heat-templates to create
one container configuration interface that will allow us to
configurably generate per-service config files. It looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;manifest: the puppet manifest to use to generate config files (Thanks to composable services this is now per service!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;puppet_tags: the puppet tags to execute within this manifest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;config_image: the docker image to use to generate config files. Generally we use the same image as the service itself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;config_volume: where to output the resulting config tree (includes /etc/ and some other directories).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then we've created a custom tool to drive this per-service configuration
called docker-puppet.py. The tool supports using the information above in a
Json file format drive generation of the config files in a single action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It ends up working like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/lqDWkBzetFk"&gt;Video demo: Docker Puppet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And thats it. Our config interfaces are intact. We generate the config files
we need. And we get to carry on with our efforts to deploy with containers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Links:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://git.openstack.org/cgit/openstack/puppet-tripleo/tree/lib/puppet/parser/functions/noop_resource.rb"&gt;puppet noop_resource function&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://review.openstack.org/#/c/416421/29/docker/docker-puppet.py"&gt;docker_puppet.py source code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><category term="tripleo"></category><category term="openstack"></category><category term="puppet"></category></entry><entry><title>TripleO: onward dark owl</title><link href="https://dprince.github.io/tripleo-onward-dark-owl.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-04T18:00:00-04:00</published><author><name>Dan Prince</name></author><id>tag:dprince.github.io,2016-08-04:tripleo-onward-dark-owl.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Onward dark owl" src="https://dprince.github.io/images/dark_owl.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was on PTO last week and started hacking on the beginnings of what could
be a new Undercloud installer that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses a single process Heat (heat-all)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It does not require MySQL, Rabbit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses noauth (no Keystone)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drives the deployment locally via os-collect-config&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prototype ends up looking like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;openstack undercloud deploy --templates&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;/root/tripleo-heat-templates
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A short presentation of the reasons behind this and demo of the prototype is available here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=y1qMDLAf26Q"&gt;Video demo: TripleO onward dark owl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An etherpad with links to the code/patches is here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://etherpad.openstack.org/p/tripleo-composable-undercloud"&gt;Etherpad&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="tripleo"></category><category term="openstack"></category></entry><entry><title>TripleO: remote execution</title><link href="https://dprince.github.io/tripleo-remote-execution.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-06-20T17:00:00-04:00</published><author><name>Dan Prince</name></author><id>tag:dprince.github.io,2016-06-20:tripleo-remote-execution.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I had a chance to sit down with Steve Baker at the OpenStack Austin Summit and
&lt;a href="https://review.openstack.org/310966"&gt;prototype a custom Mistral action&lt;/a&gt; that can drive Heat software deployments.
Iterating on that idea a bit further I have since posted a few
&lt;a href="https://etherpad.openstack.org/p/tripleo-remote-execution"&gt;patches&lt;/a&gt; which
demonstrate a new remote execution feature in TripleO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#execute a shell script on a specific server name&lt;/span&gt;
openstack overcloud execute --server-name&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;overcloud-controller-0 test.sh

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#execute a shell script on only the compute nodes&lt;/span&gt;
openstack overcloud execute --server-name&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;compute test.sh

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#execute a shell script on all overcloud nodes&lt;/span&gt;
openstack overcloud execute --server-name&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;overcloud test.sh
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A couple of things to highlight:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is API driven.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It does not use ssh (rather it uses our TripleO os-collect-config agent).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relies on Heat software deployments for much of its functionality the same
  way we do deployments in TripleO today.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Power is in the workflows... but the CLI work is cool and demonstrates it nicely.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A short demo of the new TripleO Newton feature here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Hb-Y8AqVt1E"&gt;Video demo: TripleO remote execute&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="tripleo"></category><category term="openstack"></category></entry><entry><title>Mistral workflow demo for TripleO</title><link href="https://dprince.github.io/mistral-workflow-demo-for-tripleo.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-12-07T09:14:00-05:00</published><author><name>Dan Prince</name></author><id>tag:dprince.github.io,2015-12-07:mistral-workflow-demo-for-tripleo.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A demonstration of how we might use Mistral as a workflow tool in TripleO:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bnAT37O-sdw"&gt;Video demo: Mistral workflow demo for TripleO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="tripleo"></category><category term="openstack"></category></entry></feed>